In the last segment we talked about the
CBC-MAC and the NMAC, but throughout
上一节课我们讨论了CBC-MAC和NMAC
the segment we always assumed that the
message length was a multiple of the block
但是在那一节里我们总是假定明文长度是分组长度的倍数
size. In this segment, we're going to see
what to do when the message length is not
在这节里 我们来看看当明文长度不是分组长度的倍数时该怎么做
a multiple of the block size. So recall
that the encrypted CBC mac or ECBC-MAC for
因此回忆一下 加密CBC-MAC或者简称为ECBC-MAC
short uses pseudorandom permutation F to
actually compute the CBC function as we
使用伪随机置换F来计算CBC函数
discussed in the last segment. But in the
last segment, we always assumed that the
这是我们上节讨论的 但是在上节里 我们总是假定
message itself could be broken into an
integer number of blocks for the block
明文本身可以分解成分组密码分组的整数倍
cipher. And the question is what to do
when the message length is not a multiple
那么问题就是当明文长度不是分组长度的整数倍是我们要怎么做
of the block size. So here we have a
message where the last block actually is
这里有一个明文信息 它的最后一个分组
shorter than the full block and the
question is how to compute the ECBC-MAC in
比满的分组要短 那么问题就是在这种情况下怎么计算ECBC-MAC
comes to mind is to simply pad the message
that case. So the solution of course is to
pad the message and the first pad that
答案就是填充明文 第一个想到的填充方法
with all zeros. In other words we take the
就是用全0来填充 换句话说
last block and just add zeros to it until
the last block becomes as long as one full
我们取最后一个分组 填充0直到它的长度等于满分组的长度
block size. And so my question to you is
whether the resulting MAC is secure. So
那么我给大家的问题是这样产生MAC是否是安全的
the answer is no, the MAC is not secure.
And let me explain why, basically the
答案是否 这个MAC不安全 我来解释下为什么
problem is that it's possible now to come
up with messages so that message m and the
我们很可能找出一个明文m
message m concatenated zero happen to have
exactly the same Pad. And as a result once
明文m联结0之后恰巧有有同样的填充 结果
we plug in both m and m||0 into ECBC we'll
get the same tag out, which means that
一旦我们向ECBC-MAC里插入m和m||0 我们就会输出同样的标签 这就意味着
both m and m||0 have the
same tag and therefore the attacker can
m和m||0有同样的标签 因此攻击者能够
mount an existential forgery. He would ask
for the tag on the message m. And then he
实施一个存在性伪造 他会询问明文m的标签
would output as its forgery the tag and the
message m||0. And it's
然后他会输出伪造标签和明文m||0
easy to say why that's the case. Basically, to be absolutely clear here, we have our
这是很容易就能明白为什么是这样 更清楚地来说
message m. Which after padding becomes m000. So we had to add three
我们有明文m m在填充之后变成了m000.因此我们必须加三个0
0's to it. And here we have the message m
zero, an m that ends with zero. And after
另外我们有明文m||0 以0结尾的m
padding, we basically now have to add two
0's to it. And lo and behold, they become
在填充后 我们必须再加两个0 大家看
the same pad, so that they're gonna have
exactly the same tag which allows the
它们就有了同样的填充 那么它们也会有同样的标签
adversary to mount the existential forgery
attack. So this is not a good idea. In
这就使得敌手实施存在性伪造攻击 那么这就不是一个好方法
fact appending all 0s is a terrible idea.
And if you think about concrete case where
事实上附加全0是一个糟糕的方法 如果大家想想具体的情况
this comes up imagine the automatic
clearing house system used for clearing
就会有问题 想想自动清扫房间系统
checks. I might have a check for a $100
and the tag on that check. Well, now, the
被用来处理支票 我有一张100美元的支票 上面有标签 那么现在
attacker basically could append a zero to
my check and make it a check for $1000,
攻击者能在我的支票上附加0 使它变成1000美元的支票
and that wouldn't actually change the tag.
So this ability to extend the message
实际上这不会改变标签 这种扩展明文
without changing the tag actually could
have pretty disastrous consequences. So I
而不改变标签的能力实际上有非常灾难性的后果
hope this example convinces you that the
padding function itself must be a one to
所以我希望这个例子能使大家明白填充函数本身必须是一个一一映射的函数
one function. In other words, it should be
the case that two distinct messages always
换句话说 应该是这种情况 两个不同的明文
map to two distinct padded messages. We
shouldn't actually have a collision on the
映射到不同的两个填充的明文 我们不应该在填充函数上有碰撞
padding function. Another way of saying it
is that the padding function must be
或者说 填充函数必须是可逆的
invertible. That guarantees that the
padding function is one to one. So a
这就保证了填充函数是一一映射的
standard way to do this was proposed by
the International Standards Organization
因此一种标准的实现方法被国际标准化组织ISO提出
ISO. What they suggested is basically,
let's append the string 100000 to the end
他们提议把字符创100000附在明文后面
of the message to make the message be a
multiple of the block length. Now to see
是明文长度变成分组长度的倍数 现在来看
that this padding is invertible, all we do
is describe the inversion algorithm
这个填充就是可逆的 我们要做的就是描述这个可逆算法
which simply is gonna scan the message
from right to left, until it hits the
就是简单地从右到左扫描明文 直到找到
first one and then it's gonna remove all
the bits to the right of this one,
第一个1 然后移除这个1右面的所有比特
including the one. And you see that once
we've removed the pattern this way, we
包括这个1 并且你能看到一旦我们按这种方式移除一部分
obtain the original message. So here's an
example, so here we have a message where
我们就能得到原始的明文 这有一个例子 我们有一个明文
the last block happens to be shorter than
the block length, and then we
它的最后一个分组比分组长度短
append the 1,0,0 string to it.
It's very easy to see what the pad is,
我们就把1 0 0字符串附加在它后面 很容易就能看出来填充位是什么
simply look for the first one from the
right, we can remove this pad and recover
从右边看 找到第一个1 我们可以移除这些填充位
the original message back. Now there's one
corner case that's actually quite
然后我们就恢复了原始明文 现在有一种极端情况 实际上挺重要的
important, and that is what do we do if
the original message length is already the
那是如果原始明文已经是分组长度的倍数 我们该怎么办
multiple of a block size? In that case
it's really very, very important that we
那种情况下 这么做非常非常重要的
add an extra dummy block. That contains
the pad 1000. And again, I can't tell you
加一个假的分组 包括填充1000 我都不知道
how many products and standards have
actually made this mistake where they
有多少产品和标准犯过这种错误
didn't add a dummy block and as a result,
the MAC is insecure because there's an
他们没有加一个假分组 结果MAC就不安全了
easy existential forgery attack. And let
me show you why. So suppose in case the
因为这有一个很简单的存在性伪造攻击 我来给大家说明原因 假定这种情况下
message is a multiple of a block length,
suppose we didn't add a dummy block and we
明文长度是分组长度的倍数 我们没有附加假分组
literally MAC-ed this message here. Well,
the result now is that if you look at
我们计算这个信息的MAC 结果是
the message which is a multiple of the
block size and a message which is not a
如果你看这个信息长度是分组的倍数
multiple of the block size but is padded
to the block size, and imagine it so
还有一个信息的长度不是分组长度的倍数 但它被补齐到分组的大小了
happens that this message m prime one
happens to end with 1-0-0. At this point,
想象一下 这个信息m以100结尾
you realize that here, the original
message. Here, let me draw it this way.
这里大家发现 这个原信息 我这样画
You realize that the original message
after padding. Would become identical to
你发现原信息补齐之后
the second message that was not padded at
all. And as a result, if I ask for the tag
与第二个没补齐的相同
on this message over here, I would obtain
also the tag on the second message that
因此 如果我问这个信息的标签 我也获得了第二个以100结尾的信息的标签
happened to end in 1-0-0. Okay, so if we
didn't add the dummy block, basically,
好 如果我们不加假的分组
again, the pad would be not invertible,
because two different messages, two
补齐将不是可逆的 因为两个不同的信息
distinct messages, happen to map to the
same padded result. Again, as a result,
正好被映射到了相同的补齐结果
the MAC becomes insecure. So to summarize,
this ISO standard is a perfectly fine way
这样MAC就不安全了 总结一下 这个ISO标准是完美的补齐方法
to pad, except you have to remember also
to add a dummy block in case message is a
但大家要记住也要加假的分组
multiple of the block length to begin
with. Now some of you might be wondering
当信息长度是分组长度的倍数时 现在也许有人想知道
if there is a padding scheme that never
needs to add a dummy block, and the answer
是否有一种补齐方式 从不需要加假的分组
is that if you look at a deterministic
padding function, then it's pretty easy to
答案是 如果你看确定的补齐函数
argue that there will always be cases
where we need to pad, and the reason is
容易证明所有情况下我们都需要补齐
just literally the number of messages that
are multiples of the block length is much
原因是长度为分组倍数的信息数
smaller than the total number of messages
that need not be a multiple of the block
比长度不必是分组倍数的信息数目少得多
length. And as a result we can't have a
one to one function from this bigger
因此我们不能获得一个从大的所有信息的集合
set of all messages to the smaller set of
messages which are a multiple of
到小的分组倍数长的信息集合的一一映射
the block length. There will always be cases
where we have to extend the original
总会有我们必须扩展原信息的情况
message and in this case that would
correspond to adding this dummy padding
这种情况就对应于加假的补齐分组
block. However, there is a very clever
idea called CMAC which shows that using a
但是 有一个非常聪明的方法叫CMAC
randomized padding function we can avoid
having to ever add a dummy block. And so
可以使用一个随机的补齐函数 不用加假分组了
let me explain how CMAC works. So CMAC
actually uses three keys. And, in fact,
我来解释一下CMAC如何工作 CMAC使用了三个密钥
sometimes this is called a three key
construction. So this first key, K, is
事实上这叫做三密钥机制 第一个密钥K
used in the CBC, the standard CBC MAC
algorithm. And then the keys, K1 and K2,
用于CBC计算 标准的CBC-MAC算法 然后密钥k1和k2
are used just for the padding scheme at
the very, very last block. And in fact in
仅用于补齐最后一个分组
the CMAC standard, the keys K1, K2 are
derived from the key K by some sort of a
事实上在CMAC标准中 密钥k1和k2是由密钥k推出的
pseudo random generator. So the way CMAC
works is as follows. Well, if the message
使用某种伪随机数发生器 CMAC如下工作
happens to not be a multiple of a block
length, then we append the ISO padding to
如果信息长度正好是分组长度的整数倍 那么我们采用ISO补齐方法
it. But then we also XOR this last
block with a secret key, K1, that the
但我们还要把这最后一个分组和密钥k1异或
adversary doesn't know. However, if the
message is a multiple of the block length,
攻击者不知道k1 但是如果信息长度是分组长度的倍数
then of course, we don't append anything
to it. But we XOR it with a different
那么当然 我们不做扩展 而是与另一密钥k2异或
key, K2, that, again, the adversary
doesn't actually know. So it turns out,
攻击者也不知道k2
just by doing that, it's now impossible to
apply the extension attacks that we could
这样做的话 不可能实施对级联函数、原CBC所适用的扩展攻击
do on the cascade function, and on
raw CBC. Because the poor
因为可怜的攻击者
adversary actually doesn't know what is
the last block that went into the
不知道最后分组运行了哪个函数
function. He doesn't know K1, and therefore,
he doesn't know the value at this
他不知道k1 因此他不知道这个点的值
particular point and as a result, he can't do
an extension attack. In fact, this is a
所以他无法实施扩展攻击 事实上
provable statement. And so that this
construction here is simply by XOR-ing
这个命题可以证明 这个机制就是简单地
K1 or XOR-ing K2 is really a PRF.
Despite not having to do a final
异或k1或是异或k2 是个PRF 尽管不需要做原CBC函数后面的
最终加密步骤 那么这是一个好处
encryption step after the raw CBC
function is computed. So, that's one
没有最终加密 那么好处是
benefit, that there's no final encryption
step. And the second benefit is that we resolve
我们解决了“是否发生了补齐”所带来的歧义
this ambiguity between whether padding did
happen or padding didn't happen by using
通过使用两个密钥来区分 “信息长度是分组长度的倍数”
two different keys to distinguish the case
that the message is a multiple of the block
与信息长度不是分组长度的倍数 而我们补齐了这两种情况
length versus the case where it's not but
we have a pad appended to the message. So
两个不同的密钥解决了两种情况之间的歧义
the two distinct keys resolve this
ambiguity between the two cases, and as a
因此这个补齐是充分安全的 所以如我所说
result, this padding actually is
sufficiently secure. And as I said,
CMAC有一个漂亮的定理告诉我们
there's actually a nice security theorem
that goes with CMAC that shows that the
CMAC机制是一个伪随机函数 具有与
CMAC construction really is a pseudo-random
function, with the same security
CBC-MAC相同的安全性 那么我想提醒一下
properties as CBC-MAC. So I wanted to
mention that CMAC is a federal standard
CMAC是NIST标准化的联邦标准 如果大家最近想用CBC-MAC
standardized by NIST and if you now, these
days, wanted to use a CBC-MAC for
还是去用CMAC吧 作为标准方法
anything, you would actually be using CMAC
as the standard way to do it. But
特别是在CMAC中 底层函数是AES
particularly in CMAC, the underlying block
cypher is AES and that gives us a secure
可以给我们一个由AES推出的安全的CBC-MAC
本节完结 下节我们讨论
CBC-MAC derived from AES. So that's the end
on the segment and in the next segment
一个并行的MAC机制
we'll talk about a parallel MAC.